
Power BI DAX Calculations Documentation

This document outlines the DAX formulas used in the Power BI dashboard to calculate **average profit**, **sum of profit**, and related metrics for visualizations such as "Total Profit by Geo", "Sum of Amount by Product", and profit-related tables.



Measures Used:

1. Total Amount

Total Amount = SUM(Sales[Amount])

This measure calculates the total sales amount across all transactions.



2. Total Profit

Total Profit = SUM(Sales[Profit])

This measure sums up the total profit from all sales.



3. Average Profit

Average Profit = AVERAGE(Sales[Profit])

Returns the average profit per transaction or data row.


4. Profit Percentage

Profit % = 
DIVIDE(
    [Total Profit],
    [Total Amount],
    0
)
Computes the profit percentage with safe division, handling zero-denominators gracefully.



5. Total Profit by Geo
Used in the bar chart to break down total profit by geographic region.

Total Profit by Geo = CALCULATE([Total Profit], ALLEXCEPT(Sales, Sales[Geo]))




6. Sum of Amount by Product
Used in the bar chart that shows total sales amount by product.

Sum of Amount by Product = CALCULATE([Total Amount], ALLEXCEPT(Sales, Sales[Product]))




7. Sum of Amount by Team
Used in the pie chart for team-based performance.
Sum of Amount by Team = CALCULATE([Total Amount], ALLEXCEPT(Sales, Sales[Team]))




Dataset Assumptions:
The above DAX formulas are based on the following columns in the dataset:
- Sales[Amount] – Sale value per product
- Sales[Profit] – Profit earned per sale
- Sales[Geo] – Region name (India, USA, etc.)
- Sales[Product] – Product name
- Sales[Team] – Sales team (Delish, Juicies, etc.)

---

Notes:
- DIVIDE() is used for safety instead of `/` to avoid divide-by-zero errors.
- ALLEXCEPT() ensures that filters on other fields don’t interfere with grouped aggregations.
- Use formatting in Power BI to show percentages, currency (₹ or $), or M (Millions) as required.


